Welcome back to AM Northwest.
From cool scientific
instruments to old maps,
we always learn something
new with our next guest.
Here to share a science-based collection,
we welcome back antique
appraiser Gary Germer.
Great to see you.
How are you doing, Helen?
Thanks for having me back.
Okay, you love maps, is that right?
I'm basically a hobbit, you know.
I'm ready to go off on an
adventure, at least to look at one.
We have this great
collection of stuff come in
that's a lot of, you know, 18th century,
that's during the 1700s when so
much world exploration was going on.
These are samplings of some of the maps
and just how they would make them.
The one below here is
South America in 17...
That was printed in 1786.
Yeah, wow.
So it's really old.
They would guess what was in the
inside because it hadn't been explored.
So if you look at the map, you'll
see around the edges they have it.
And then this one here
is also South America,
and it's 1880.
And then this one here is 1850.
Much more filled in.
So these were all the
explorers as they went.
They would then map, and
they got better and better.
Wow.
This map is of the United
States, and it's...
Really.
They didn't know much of anything.
I forgot the date on it. I apologize.
1761.
Wow.
Before the Revolutionary War, and we see
the East Coast is pretty much filled in.
Right.
The West Coast is just kind of a mess.
Wow.
And those are when map collectors
really loved that sort of thing.
So you kind of see how the science grew.
The history.
And the history of it all.
I mean, you see the history of it all.
Yeah.
That's incredible.
And so I love maps.
We have a ton of them that came in of different
eras and different parts of the world.
Yeah.
And it's a lot of fun.
And then the equipment.
This here...
I know you love telescopes.
Me and my telescopes.
Yeah.
These two pieces would
have been on a ship.
And this one I already
pulled out the cap off.
Would have been on a ship
and mounted on a ship.
Okay.
And, you know, as you can see
through and makes it look like...
I don't know if you can see
any of it through or not.
I can't really, yeah.
Yeah.
It's kind of hard in here.
Right.
But this would have been what would
have been mounted permanently.
All of the officers back in the 1700s had to
have their own little, you know, the pull.
Oh.
So everybody had their own.
Their own.
This would have been up on
the crow's nest up high.
Right.
Permanently set there.
Okay.
1750.
Wow.
1942.
World War II.
Same thing.
Yeah.
The optics, interestingly, they had perfected
the grinding of the lenses back in that time.
Yeah.
So there hasn't been
much of an improvement.
This was much more of an
improvement as far as the casing.
Can you see farther away with this one?
Yeah.
Well, they did.
And they arranged it if you see farther.
Now, of course, with radar and stuff,
they don't need it as much as before.
Yeah.
You know.
Still fascinating.
It's just kind of neat that it hadn't...
The whole idea hadn't changed
in 200 years that much.
So let me ask you, do you know
the prices of any of these?
Like what someone could get for it?
For a PC?
For a PC.
Surprisingly, I think
they're fairly affordable.
A piece like this is around $300.
Okay.
And this, the World War
II, $1,250 in that range.
So not huge money.
Yeah.
But I think it makes it affordable.
I brought this microscope
because this is 1840.
Yeah.
And it has a chain drive in it.
And it's the very first time that they used,
in order for it to glide up and down, before
they had to kind of pull it.
And it wasn't as accurate.
Now they can just...
This has a mechanism.
And it was the first time
they came up with it.
So this makes it a historic
microscope for people to use it.
Have the lens on the side to direct light
down to the mirror that then shoots it up.
So the principle is still the same.
Right.
As modern microscopes.
But being an antique one, this is kind of a
sort of a landmark, the first of a period,
which I thought was kind of fun.
Wow.
Yeah.
That's great history.
Love it.
English.
And this is about $2,500.
Okay.
Because of its interest.
Gotcha.
What do we have?
What do we have in here?
This is the box for this.
Oh, really?
Yeah, that's the carrying case for it.
I think that's kind of cool.
Yeah, it has all fitted for the...
You can open it up if you want.
Yeah.
It's all fitted for it to...
And more of the lenses
from the top eyepieces.
Look at that.
So it can have closer...
But depending on what you're looking at.
Right.
The slides, you're doing
what you need to do.
Okay.
This is for...
This is a little bit later.
This is actually Japanese,
but everybody had one.
This is for, like, trench warfare.
So you can sit underneath and
have the periscope looking above.
So you have binoculars here, but you can hide
behind the hill and look and see what's going
on.
You can see...
Oh.
Or hide below.
Okay.
Or they can turn the base and it
can go into a thing to hold it up.
So...
I can see this stoler cam.
Yeah, I can see that.
Yeah, I think they're...
That's wild.
Isn't that crazy?
Yeah.
I just thought things like that.
Also, what I think is great is for...
In a way, like, for decorating a man's
office or a library or something like that.
Right.
Yeah.
Or whatever.
That's incredible.
Now, is this the case that that came in?
That's the case.
And it has the Japanese guy's name
on it, who they liberated it from.
Yeah.
Oh, right.
Yes.
Who they took it from.
Gotcha.
Yeah, that's great.
Okay.
Wow.
And this is one of my favorite things.
This is called a binocular telescope.
And this would have been used in a
library, in a wealthy man's library.
He'd look out for, like, bird watching.
You can move it.
You put it on a table and it can turn.
Oh.
That turns that way.
And then you can roll it
to where you need it to be.
So, it's very stable.
Is this your personal collection?
No, no.
This is part of a collection
we're working with.
Okay.
Gotcha.
This fellow was kind
of crazy about optics.
And we have tons of lenses
and other microscopes.
Yeah.
But these are my favorite ones that I pulled
out of the collection to share with everyone.
Wow.
Okay.
We want to take a look
at the U.S. map again.
Okay.
Because we find that fascinating.
So, tell me a little bit more.
So, like, the East Coast, as
you mentioned, is pretty filled.
And as we can see, West
Coast, not so much.
Yeah.
1861.
And what I think is funny about it is you can see
the Gulf of California there is way over-exaggerated.
But even for the Pacific Northwest where
we are, you know, that's supposed to be.
See this?
I don't know if I can point at it.
Where's that?
Right in here.
Yes.
Everything's upside down for me.
That would have been the Strait of Wanda Fuga,
but it's a little bit over-exaggerated as well.
Yeah.
And so they had just started exploring,
really getting to explore the West Coast,
and they were still making maps.
And so a lot of it was on, again, the inland
was more about stories that they heard this was
there.
And so they kind of tried to map it out
accordingly as best that they could.
Yeah.
But this is, like I said, this
is the age of exploration.
It was a great time in
history to, and to collect.
I mean, you can find these wonderful maps.
Now, maps of Europe at the time
you'll find same time period.
I mean, they've lived there forever.
Yes.
So they're already detailed.
Oh, they already know all the details.
Yeah.
All right.
Gary, excellent pieces.
This is pretty wild.
It was fun.
Thank you so much.
All right.
We'll be right back
with more AM Northwest.
Don't go away.
Thanks.